Guide to the Park City Mountain Resort audio-visual collection 1961-2002
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
Park City Mountain Resort audio-visual collection
1961-2002
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 (801) 581-8864
A0664
Park City Mountain Resort
Approximatley 210 VHS videocassettes, 33 U-matic videocassettes, 23 Betacam videocassettes, 3 Hi-8 videocassettes, 5 1-inch videotapes, 27 16mm films, 2 8mm films, 22 audiocassettes, 6 reel-to-reel audiotapes, 1 CD-ROM and 3 1/4-inch tape data cartridges.
The Park City Mountain Resort audio-visual collection (1961-2002) contains film, video and audio recordings, almost all of which are directly related to Park City Mountain Resort's role in Utah's winter sports industry and international competative ski ciruit. The colleciton includes promotional materials for the ski area, Utah's ski industry at large and the United States Ski Team, footage of the World Cup and other competitions held at the resort, ski films by Stein Ericksen and Warren Miller, and many other materials relating to the ski and snowboard industry in Utah and beyond. Founded in 1963, Park City Mountain Resort is one of three ski areas in the vicinity of Park City, Utah.
Organizational History
The town of Park City sprung up in Utah's Wasatch Mountains after army prospectors discovered silver in the area in 1868. Early miners used primitive skis and snowshoes as transporation to the mines, and skiing emerged a recreational activity by the 1920s. Scandinavian miners held jumping tournaments on the Creole Mine dump (now the Creole ski run to the Town Lift), and the newly formed Park City Ski Club conducted guided ski tours on the hills that make up the modern resort.
As the area's silver mining industry faded away in the mid 20th century, the town's last surviving mining company, United Park City Mines, received a federal loan to help revive conomically depressed rural towns and opened the city's first ski area, Treasure Mountain Resort, in 1963.
For its first four years of operation the resort featured the Skier's Subway lift, which carried skiers in modified mining trolleys two and a half miles through the pitch dark Spiro Tunnel to the Thaynes Hoist, where they boarded the old mine elevator and were lifted 1,750 feet to the surface near the Thaynes chair lift.
Treasure Mountain changed its name to Park City Ski Area in 1966 and to Park City Mountain Resort in 1996. Its sister ski resort, Park City West (later Wolf Mountain; now The Canyons) opened in 1968, and nearby Deer Valley opened in 1981.
Park City hosted its first World Cup ski race in 1986. During the 2002 Winter Olympic Games hosted by Salt Lake City, Park City Mountain Resort hosted the men's and women's giant slalom, men's and women's snowboarding parallel giant slalom, and both men's and women's snowboarding halfpipe events.
The Park City Mountain Resort audio-visual collection (1961-2002) contains film, video and audio recordings, almost all of which are directly related to Park City Mountain Resort's role in Utah's winter sports industry and international competative ski ciruit. The colleciton includes promotional materials for the ski area, Utah's ski industry at large and the United States Ski Team, footage of the World Cup and other competitions held at the resort, ski films by Stein Ericksen and Warren Miller, and many other materials relating to the ski and snowboard industry in Utah and beyond.
The majory of the materials are arranged chronologically. Undated material is located at the end of the register beginning with item 224. Some items are available on more than one format.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
See also the Park City Mountain Resort photograph collection (P0949), the Park City Ski Area photograph collection (P0384), the Park City, Utah photograph collection (P0228) and the Park City Ski Corporation records (Accn 1218). For additional promotional audio-visual materials related to Utah ski resorts see the Ski Utah tourism audio-visual collection (A0590) and the Utah Travel Council tourism video collection (A0544).
Park City (Utah)--History; Skis and skiing--Utah--Park City--History--Sources; Ski resorts--Utah--Park City--History--Sources; Skiing--Utah--History; Snowboarding; Tourism; Advertising and Marketing; Sports and Recreation; Moving Images; Sound Recordings; Moving images; Sound recordings
- Three Kings grand opening, 1961; 16mm film Color, magnetic soundtrack (Reel 1)
  This film contains images of two men getting onto a helicopter and a scene of the outdoors from the helicopter. It shows a few shots of the state capital and then shows the grand opening of the Three Kings chair lift where one of the men from the first scene cuts a red ribbon at Treasure Mountain Resort, which will open in 1963.
- Treasure Mountain raw footage 1, 1964; 16mm film Black and white, silent (Reel 2)
  This film contains raw footage of downtown Park City and of a family purchasing ski passes at the ticket booth, getting on the gondola and then skiing at Treasure Mountain Resort.
- Treasure Mountain raw footage 2, 1964; 16mm film Black and white, silent (Reel 3)
  This film contains raw footage of ski lessons at Treasure Mountain Resort and of the ski class's lunch break at the lodge.
- Treasure Mountain raw footage 3, 1964; 16mm film Black and white, silent (Reel 4)
  This film contains raw footage of a giant slalom ski race and of a hot dog ski competition held at Treasure Mountain Resort.
- Treasure Mountain raw footage 4, 1964; 16mm film Black and white, silent (Reel 5)
  This film contains raw footage of ski lessons for beginner, intermediate and advanced skiers. It also shows footage of a woman sitting in front of a fire and then shopping while her young children wait at the daycare facility at Treasure Mountain Resort.
- Untitled Park City promotional skiing film, 1966; 16mm film Color, sound (Reel 6)
  This film compares Park City in 1966 to Park City during it's silver mining era. It shows images of Civil War soldiers and Park City's mountains and the mineshafts. It then shows footage of a man being taken to a jail cell where he spends his time playing a banjo and singing. Other historical images include drawings of trains, the miners and the actual mining process, and of several men burning a certificate.
  When the images switch to 1966 several people prepare to go skiing outside of the Treasure Mountain Inn. They get onto a gondola and get off at the summit house area. There are images of the skiers and then images of evening entertainment in the town.
  At the end of the film the man in the jail is shackled to the cell wall. We see a man skiing, and finally the man form the jail steps out of the gondola and skis away.
- Utah! On My Mind, 1969; 16mm film Color, optical soundtrack (Reel 7)
  This promotional film for Utah's ski industry was presented by Telescene Inc. It includes footage of the mountains at Park City, people traveling with their skis and then skiing, and footage from the hot dog ski competition at Alta.
- Stein Turned On, 1969; 16mm film Color, sound (Reel 8)
  This film about Olympian Stein Ericksen's career at Park City begins with footage of Ericksen organizing and teaching ski classes for beginning and advanced students. Footage of Ericksen setting up a picnic on the snow is followed by more ski lessons, Ericksen helicopter skiing, and Ericksen teaching slalom ski racing.
- The Ski Scene, 1969; 16mm film Color, sound (Reel 9)
  This film is a Warren Miller production and presented by Terracor. It features backcountry powder skiing, ballet skiing, the Sun Valley Farriman Cup Race, ski crashes and stunts, and a ski trip to Japan.
- Park City Swings, 1970; 16mm film Color, optical soundtrack (Reel 10)
  This film is a Warren Miller production. It begins with various shots of Park City and its surrounding ski areas. Several skiers go into the Park City mines on a small train (probably Treasure Mountain Resort's early Skier's Subway lift). The following scenes are of these men extreme skiing at Park City.
  2 reels
- De L'acier a la Neige, 1970; 16mm film Color, optical soundtrack, French subtitles (Reel 11)
  This advertisement for Solomon ski equipment begins with images of ski racers and a woman's hand turning a ski boot attachment. Then you see the Solomon building where men are designing ski parts and machines are making the parts. The film ends with a short summary of the film interspersed with the Solomon logo.
- Ski America, 1971; 16mm film Color, sound (Reel 12)
  This film showcases nine Rocky Mountain ski resorts including Aspen, Jackson Hole, Steamboat, Taos, Breckenridge, Park City, Sun Valley, Vail, and Winter Park. The featured skiers are Billy Kidd, Roger Staub, Jeff Jobe, Tom Leroi, Paul Pfosi, Arthur Furrer, Bill Peterson, Herman Gollner, Jean Claude Killy, Stein Eriksen, Ruedi Wyrsch, Pepi Stiegler, Corky Fowler, and Suzy Chaffee.
- Stein ski touring, 1972; 16mm film Color, sound (Reel 13)
  This film features Stein Eriksen leading a group of five people into the backcountry on cross-country skis.
- Hot dog contest skiing at Park City, 1972; 16mm film Color, sound (Reel 14)
  This film contains footage from a hot dog skiing competition held at Park City. The contest includes skiers doing back flips and skiing moguls.
- Leo Kottke concert, 1972 September 19; 16mm film Color, black and white, silent, magnetic soundtrack (Reel 15)
  a) This is the original film of the Leo Kottke Concert in an outdoor amphitheater in Park City Utah filmed by the Park City Film Group (silent).
  b) The same concert footage in black and white (work print, silent).
  c) Magnetic soundtracks for films a and b.
- Barf-O-Rama, 1972-1973; 8mm film Color, silent (Reel 16)
  This film contains footage of skiers skiing in a single file line, playing leapfrog on skis, and bunny hopping in place.
- Deep Duck, 1973; 8mm film Color, silent (Reel 17)
  This film contains footage of an amateur play preformed on skis. The play begins with a classroom full of people. The villain of the play disrupts the class by running out. The next image is of a rubber ducky floating in swampy grass. The villain skis by the rubber ducky and stops to give some children a snack. Then you see the villain in the locker room stealing lunches. Next the villain kidnaps a young women and skis away with her. A young man sees the villain and starts to chase him; the villain knocks the girl out and skis away. The girl is rescued, but the villain later catches up to the rescuer and attacks him. This leads into a high-speed chase that ends with the villain being caught.
- Ski the Sky, 1974; 16mm film Color, optical soundtrack (Reel 18)
  This film was produced for Big Sky of Montana and Hart Ski Company by The Film Factory.
  Director: Jim Cotter
  Writer: Duane Johnson
  Music: Dale Mentea
  The film begins with shots of skiers interspersed with shots of a red hot air balloon with "Ski the Sky" written on it. After some scenic shots from the sky, the balloon lands and there are more images of skiers. The scene shifts to the lodge restaurant and bar where tired skiers eat sandwiches, have a few drinks and dance. Next there are images of cross-country skiers, a horse-drawn sled, and people of all ages getting ready to go alpine skiing. The closing image is of the red hot air balloon leaving the ski area.
- Skiing Park City, 1976 December 14; 16mm film Black and white, color, sound (Reel 19)
  a-c) Olympic Medal winner Stein Eriksen takes you powder skiing through winter beauty, down a slalom course, over a summersault jump and through a few moguls. Then he leads you to the resort lobby where food and entertainment take over. Produced by Dick Barrymore Productions Inc.
  d) This same film, this time introduced by a short black and white clip from the 1960's and 1970's which contains free skiing, downhill racing and footage of the torch run which is when several skiers organize a night skiing event in which each individual attaches road flares to the ends of their poles, hold them out at a ninety degree angle and ski down the hill.
- The Spirit Of The West, 1978 November 28; 16mm film Color, sound (Reel 20)
  a-c) This film is a Warren Miller production in which the spirit of an 'old timer' takes the viewer on a journey through time from the Old West to the modern ski resorts. It features skiing on the slopes and other resort activities.
  d) The same film narrated in Japanese.
  e) A very similar film used as a promotional video by United Airlines.
- Randy's film, 1978; 16mm film Color, sound (Reel 21)
  This film contains raw footage of ski jumping, dog sled racing, a torch run, and downhill skiing.
- Ski and Ski Better, 1982; 16mm film Color, sound (Reel 22)
  a-c) A detailed how-to film for the novice skier. Ski instructors conduct classes on skiin techniques at Utah ski resorts.
  d-e) Revised versions of the film.
- Utah: The Greatest Snow on Earth short version, 1983; 16mm film Color, optical sound (Reel 23)
  A promotional film for Utah's ski industry.
- Skiercise, 1983; VHS videocassette (Cassette 24)
  This video was produced by Dean Stephen Lyras. It is an exercise film that gets you in shape for skiing. There are seven 10-minute segments and each segment contains a workout designed specifically to strengthen one type of skiing: freestyle, helicopter skiing, ballet, telemark, and cross-country. Each segment is started out by a group of girls demonstrating each move. After this, there is footage of the type of skiing that corresponds to that particular workout.
- Park City Ski, 1984 April 12; VHS videocassette (Cassette 25)
  Produced by Rocky Mountain Motion Pictures. This is footage of a womens giant slalom ski race. It shows the women at the starting gate, in the middle of the course, the scoring returns and the awards ceremony. There are interviews with the top two racers at the end of the film.
- Channel 5/Coca Cola Cup, 1985 February 03; VHS videocassette (Cassette 26)
  This video shows highlights from the fifth week of the 1985 Channel Five/Coca Cola Cup Race event at Park City Utah. This event is a giant slalom race on a course that drops 400 vertical feet and has 27 gates. The event is open to amateur skiers of all ages.
  KSL's Jim Derkir narrates the video and reviews slope conditions and the history of Park City Ski Area. Before the races, Stein Eriksen gives a few racing tips. The results from the various age groups are reviewed, as are the results of all of the first place winners are reviewed.
- Park City Ski Area rough cut, 1985 July 11; VHS videocassette (Cassette 27)
  Rough cut of an advertising film in which a family decides to travel to Park City, Utah to ski. It includes footage of Park City's facilities, restaurants, bars, and ski slopes. Featured terrain includes backcountry powder, moguls, groomed hills, and trees. The film also advertises Celebrity Ski Classics, which take place on the Park City race hills.
  2 cassettes. The same footage repeated eight times.
- U.S. Ski Team Celebrity Ski Classic, 1985 October 15; VHS videocassette (Cassette 28)
  The Celebrity Classic is a ski-racing event that is held yearly to raise funds for the United States (U.S.) Ski Team. The teams consist of athletes, celebrities, and sponsors. The races include head to head competition on parallel racecourses and individual "grudge" races. The individual "grudge" races consist of racing down the course with one ski, going down the course skiing backwards, having to tow a person in a toboggan behind you, or sliding down the course with two people on one piece of plastic. To wrap the event up, participants head indoors to hear Michel Martin Murphy perform followed by a few words from many loyal sponsors of the U.S. Ski Team.
- "Ski Park City", "Ski Vacation", 1985 December 11; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 29)
  This video contains two thirty-second advertisements. The first advertises a contest in which you could win a ski vacation to Park City, Utah. The second advertises Park City Ski Area's vast terrain and the resort's facilities.
- Heli-High, 1985 December 26; 16mm film Color, sound (Reel 30)
  Canadian Mountain Holidays (CMH) Heli-skiing presents "Heli-High," produced and directed by Dick Barrymore. This film is shot at Estar Base, which includes the Pucells, Selkirks, Monashees and Cariboos mountains. There is also footage from Val D'Isere, Zermatt, Chamonix, Aspen and Snowbird. The footage consists of skiers being dropped off at the top of a mountain by a helicopter and skiing down. It also shows how it is determined which mountains are the safest to heli-ski on by means of examining various snow layers.
- Special Olympics, 1985; VHS videocassette (Cassette 31)
  This is a sixteen-minute coverage of the 1985 Special Olympics by Turner Broadcasting System (TBS) Sports. The footage includes the opening ceremonies, the giant slalom event, the downhill event, speed skating, figure skating, celebrity racing, and the closing ceremonies.
  3 cassettes
- Park City Ski Area: Of All the Places in the World, 1985; VHS videocassette (Cassette 32)
  Promotional video for Park City Ski Area.
- Summerside, 1985; VHS videocassette (Cassette 33)
  This is a promotional video for Park City's summer activities. Activities include golfing, tennis, hiking, horseback riding, hot air ballooning, water skiing, arts festivals, and live music indoors and out.
  2 cassettes
- Winter in Park City, Utah, 1985; VHS videocassette (Cassette 34)
  This is a promotional video for Park City's winter activities. A few of the activities included are alpine skiing at one of the three surrounding resorts, cross country skiing at Jeremy Ranch, backcounty dog sled tours, snowshoeing, and hot air ballooning.
- America's Opening World Cup, 1986 January 26; VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette (Cassette 35)
  This World Cup, held at Park City Ski Area, was the first World Cup in North America ever. This video contains footage of the Opening Ceremonies held at the University of Utah followed by the Salt Lake City Ski Ball at the Westin Hotel Utah. The featured races are the women's slalom and the women's giant slalom. After the races, a few words are said at the World Cup Closing Dinner.
- America's Opening World Cup advertisements - "The Festival" and "The Flag Racing", 1986 February 12; 1986 March 11; VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette (Cassette 36)
  This video contains two promotional clips: one is for the U.S. Womens ski team and the other is for an event called the U.S. Ski Team Versus the World. Each promotional clip is 30 seconds long and gives dates, times, locations and ticket information.
- America's Opening World Cup advertisements, 1986 November 03; VHS videocassette (Cassette 37)
  This video has two promotional clips for Americas Opening World Cup ski races. The first one is a ten second version which gives the date, time and location. The second one is thirty seconds long and it gives a few facts, the date, time, location and ticket information.
- America's Opening World Cup - Birney revised, 1986 November; 1-inch videotape (Reel 38)
  No description is provided because 1-inch videotape could not be played at our facility at the time this collection was processed. However, our capabilities are constantly changing. Please contact a multimedia archivist about the current possibility of viewing this material.
- Hyrum W. Smith seminar review tape, 1986; Audiocassette (Cassette 39)
  Hyrum W. Smith, one of the founders of the Franklin Institute Inc. and senior vice president of marketing, conducts a seminar on time management and organizational skills.
- Park City World Cup invitation raw footage, 1986; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 40)
  This video contains raw footage of Craig Badami, the vice president of Park City Ski Area, inviting everyone to welcome home the U.S. Women's Ski Team as they take on the world at the Park City World Cup ladies slalom event.
- Park City Travelview, 1987 March 05; VHS videocassette (Cassette 41)
  This is a promotional video for Park City Ski Area. It promotes both the town and the terrain with clips of city and ski slop activities. The advertised terrain includes groomed hills, backcountry powder, moguls, race hills and trees.
- KPCW - Utah Symphony announcement 41, 1987 May 05; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 42)
  Radio advertisement for the Utah Symphony. 30 seconds.
- Park City Ski Area television news coverage, 1987 September 03; VHS videocassette (Cassette 43)
  The first story covered on this video is about the Park City Midmountain Lodge, a historical building in Park City Utah, which was moved five hundred feet up the mountain and turned into a restaurant.
  The second story is about the upcoming Pro Cup Ski Race at Park City Ski Resort. News reporters interview Mark Menlove, Holly Flanders and Scott Hofmann.
- Ski In: Snowbird, Utah, 1987 October 08; VHS videocassette (Cassette 44)
  Jack Eddies Ski In honors the best skiing in North America and offers information on what is happening in the Western ski areas. In this episode Eddie visits Snowbird, Utah where he features the terrain, the Cliff Lodge, the racing competition, the friendly atmosphere and the beautiful scenery.
- Park City Pro Cup, 1987 November 09; 1-inch videotape (Reel 45)
- Ski Utah, 1987; VHS videocassette (Cassette 46)
  Promotional film produced by Travelview International. The video contains a 22-minute feature about Utah's ski areas, a reference guide providing information on Utah's ski resorts in Utah, lodging and accommodation tips, dining and tourist oriented services, and a Travel Tips segment.
- Deer Valley Resort, 1987-1988; VHS videocassette (Cassette 47)
  This promotional video showcases Deer Valley's ski terrain, lodging, food, services, and summer season events.
- Park City Senators Ski Cup, 1988 January 13-14; VHS videocassette (Cassette 48)
  The Senators Ski Cup is a race that is held annually at the Park City Resort. This event was organized by former Senator Jake Garn to benefit the Primary Childrens Hospital and raises around 100,000 dollars through friendly head to head slalom races.
- Park City Senators Ski Cup, 1988 January 21; VHS videocassette (Cassette 49)
  More detailed footage of the Senators Ski race that is held annually to raise money for the Primary Childrens Hospital. The event was organized by former Senator Jake Garn and consists of a head to head competition slalom course.
- Ski Scene: Sun Valley, Idaho, 1988 January 29; VHS videocassette (Cassette 50)
  Ski Scene is a television-program that tours various ski areas to show what they have to offer. In this episode, they travel to Sun Valley, Idaho. They review the history of Sun Valley, explore the modern site and pursue recreational adventures such as downhill skiing, cross country skiing, sleigh riding, and ice skating. They also rate the accommodations, restaurants and shops.
- Canyon master plan, 1988 July 31; VHS videocassette (Cassette 51)
  This news report documents a heated controversy of developing a ski interconnect in the Wasatch Mountains. The reporter introduces the four scenarios of development followed by a discussion between Gale Dick with Save Our Canyons and Craig Badami with the Utah Ski Association. They discuss many pros and cons for each scenario.
- Park City Pro Cup revised, 1988 October 31; 1-inch videotape (Reel 52)
- Park City Pro Cup television news coverage, 1988 November 18-28; VHS videocassette (Cassette 53)